♪ [theme]
Michael: It rushed across a
country like an unstoppable tide
bringing misery and
despair to millions.
I have had a chance to see
the tremendous destruction
and profound suffering
with my own eyes.
It is heart wrenching.
The scale and magnitude
is difficult to comprehend,
beyond imagination.
Michael: On News In Review
today...
Hello, I'm Michael Serapio.
Every year the monsoon rains
arrive in Pakistan.
But this year the rainfall
was so heavy it triggered
one of the biggest natural
catastrophes in living memory.
Sweeping in from the Arabian Sea
and the Bay of Bengal the rains
mixed with melting snow
in the northern mountains
to cause massive flooding.
[people screaming]
Michael: By early August
dozens of roads, bridges
and entire villages
had been swept away.
More than a thousand people
were dead, two million
people were homeless.
"It rained for three days,"
he says. "Water kept rising.
Many people drowned."
And right from the start,
relief organisations
knew that getting help to
the needy wouldn't be easy.
The terrain, mountainous,
hot, remote,
difficult access,
political instability,
all of those
make a dangerous potion.
Michael: But as the rains
kept falling,
nobody could have predicted
the scale of the disaster.
The Pakistani army
was quickly overwhelmed.
Many areas received no aid,
and despair turned to anger.
own people, and the poorage
get nothing," this man said.
Michael: Meanwhile in Canada,
Pakistani-Canadians
were desperate for news
about their relatives.
I feel bad and again
I will say I feel helpless.
Michael: That sense of
helplessness only grew
as water continued to surge
down Pakistan's longest river,
the Indus.
The number of those affected by
the flooding continued to grow.
And as the CBC's
Adrienne Arsenault reported
from the flood zone, so did the
threat of political instability.
The monsoon rains
aren't done with Pakistan yet.
In the northwest where flooding
was supposed to be abating,
menacing skies wreck the army's
still urgent relief effort.
In the bellies of idle military
helicopters are enough supplies
to feed hundreds of
stranded people for a week,
but there's no help
coming today.
Do you think that means
they're in trouble?
They are in trouble.
They're two weeks without
anything to eat or drink.
So we have help,
but we are unable to give them.
For two days now,
these Pakistani and Afghani
military helicopters
that are loaded with relief
have been sitting here grounded
because of the driving rain.
That means two more days
that tens of thousands of people
remain completely cut off
from the most basic of help.
In parts of the northwest,
there is still some
precarious road access.
Neither government workers
nor many aid agencies
have made it through.
Falah-e-Insaniat
has been here, though,
a local charity with so many
connections, it was able to get
food aid and money out far and
fast, often on behalf of others.
On the burst banks of
the Kabul River, Rahim Khan,
a teacher who saw the waters
punch a hole in his home,
say the government's
weak response was a mistake.
Adrienne: Falah-e-Insaniat
was eager to tell us
they step in
where the government fails.
"We're providing food and
medical supplies, but
there's also a long-term plan
in which we're giving them
money," said a spokesman.
That phrase "long-term plan"
scares the Pakistani government.
It worries there are
radical Islamist groups
who will use the floods
as an opportunity to recruit,
spread a militant message,
and weaken the government.
And Falah-e-Insaniat raises
eyebrows here, often viewed
as a rebranding of
Jamat ud Dawa, a banned
organisation linked to
the militant group blamed
for the Mumbai bombings.
Jamat ud Dawa's offices
were closed last year
and these people
insist theirs is not just the
same old group with a new name.
You're not a banned
organisation?
No, no, no.
Adrienne: But as we were
leaving, the group spokesman
passed me his card. It clearly
links him to Jamat ud Dawa.
The connexion is hardly hidden.
On the ground, though,
neither Rahim Khan nor
the others in line for help
from Falah-e-Insaniat
gave the possible link
a moment's thought.
Adrienne: He doesn't care about
political motives, he says.
He knows these people simply
as the ones who showed up.
Adrienne Arsenault, CBC News,
Nowshera in north-western
Pakistan.
As the scale of the humanitarian
catastrophe continued to grow
another problem emerged.
Despite the pressing need
for emergency aid, many
countries including Canada,
were slow to respond. And as
the CBC's Briar Stewart reports,
that had some Canadians
wondering why.
At this family-run store,
the disaster in Pakistan
is a constant concern.
Nadia Ahmad's father
is there visiting relatives,
and he's had to travel through
the flood zone to reach them.
He said a lot of children were
buried, just within the ground,
and they just drowned
and nobody knows.
Briar: Ahmad remembers
how her neighbourhood
raised money after
the tsunami in 2004.
She says this disaster
doesn't seem to be generating
as urgent of a response.
I think it's really sad. Perhaps
there's a lack of awareness.
Briar: Pakistan appealed
for aid two days ago.
The Canadian government
pledged $2 million,
an amount many feel
is too small.
The minister of international
cooperation says Canada's
contribution may seem small,
but there are expectations
more will be coming.
The government insists the
relief effort must be controlled
and points to previous disasters
where aid sat for days
waiting to be delivered,
but many agencies
working on the ground
don't buy that argument.
It's almost 10 days now
that this started, you know.
Like, I find the excuse
a little bit weak.
Briar: And the public has
also been slow to respond.
Agencies are concerned
it could be due to fears
that the money might end up
in the hands of insurgents.
The floods is everywhere, it's
the whole country, you know,
from north to south.
So the Taliban don't have
a presence there, you know,
and they are a small group.
Briar: A reality Ahmad
hopes people understand.
This is sad when people
bring up politics
because it's a human being.
Briar: And right now, the United
Nations says in Pakistan,
there are six million of them
in immediate need of help.
Briar Stewart,
CBC News, Toronto.
Michael: Those numbers would
only grow, and by mid August
the U.N.'s Secretary General
declared the catastrophe
in Pakistan the worst
he had ever seen.
I have had a chance to see
the tremendous destruction
and profound suffering
with my own eyes.
It is heart-wrenching.
The scale and magnitude
is difficult to comprehend,
beyond imagination.
Michael: Ban Ki-Moon
pleaded with other countries
to step up their aid efforts.
But as the CBC's
Adrienne Arsenault reported,
even getting limited help
to the needy wasn't easy.
The Pakistani army is always
in a hurry now in Punjab
taking dozens of relief flights
daily over still flooded land.
A swath the size of the United
Kingdom looks like this now,
a vast, muddy lake
with small patches of dry land.
Even those trying to flee
might not know where to go.
The Pakistani army says it is
always ready to conduct rescues
as well as offering aid, but
it's encountering a problem:
many flood survivors
are too scared to leave
their flooding homes.
They've already lost
their crops so the last
thing they want to do is leave
their very last possessions.
So they're saying, no.
This is extremely
frustrating for the rescuers
because they know those people
are risking their lives.
Carrying water and milk,
enough for just a few days,
they land at a camp in Jampur.
Eight hundred people,
barely a hundred tents.
Many say they were chased
by the water, fled to one place
only to be flooded out again.
Others immediately sought
high ground, climbed trees
only to find snakes,
cobras have done the same.
On a bed in the heat,
Razia, who says she broke
her back in three places
when she fell off a roof
trying to escape the water.
[through Interpreter]
She's saying she's suffering
a lot over here.
That's why she needs evacuation.
Adrienne: He says she's had
a basic operation, will be
evacuated properly to a good
hospital soon but not today.
Remarkably,
the military say those here
are still in better shape
than the stubborn stranded.
I requested them, even
I placed my hands like this,
"Please come with me, come
with me," but they don't come.
They say, "We want to
protect our luggage."
Adrienne: So routinely
they drop them water and food.
Ten minutes on the ground,
that's it, and they leave.
There are more to worry about.
Flying out, the army
carries pharmacists
who are now moving
on to other camps.
There are many cases of
snake bites and malaria problem
there and diarrhoea
and skin rashes.
Skin problems and digestive
problems are mostly seen there.
Adrienne: Do you have
the anti-venom for the snake
bites?
Actually, ma'am, anti-venom,
it is very costly.
Adrienne: Back on base
and medicine is still key.
Rescued and ill kids usually end
up nearby at Multan's children's
hospital in cramped,
loud wards.
[pained crying]
Many must be treated outside.
This is dehydration,
potentially fatal diarrhoea.
Their mothers, with nowhere else
to stay, will sit here for days,
and they too are often up.
While Sakhina talks,
her family, lying beside her,
seems suddenly overwhelmed,
her sister-in-law actually
on the cellphone to her husband.
He stayed near the flooded home.
He is stuck on an embankment
surrounded by water.
"Men have been left behind
and they're worried,"
Sakhina explains.
"We can't go to them.
They can't come to us."
So here's how
this crisis spirals.
Families separated,
some getting help,
but soon to return
to grim temporary shelters
where doctors fear
they'll just get sick again.
Adrienne Arsenault,
CBC News, Multan, Pakistan.
Michael: By September
more than 20 million people
had been affected by the floods.
And with food, shelter,
and medicine all in short supply
taking care of the youngest
victims and their mothers
became a major priority.
Many women give their birth
while they are travelling.
We are giving them the relief,
whatever resources we have.
Michael: But more aid was
arriving in the stricken areas,
and the CBC's Nahlah Ayed
found one Canadian team
trying to make a difference.
This boy was so sick, his mother
worried he wouldn't make it
through the night,
but a few hours in hospital
and he's ready to go home.
They were displaced when the
rain swept their straw hut away.
Since then, three of
her children have suffered
severe vomiting and diarrhoea.
"They helped me a lot here,"
she says.
"I know they came from abroad,
but I don't know which country."
She's never even
heard of Canada.
But it was a tight team
of Canadian aid workers
who turned a stretch of road
into a small field hospital.
What they've accomplished
in just days speaks
to the possibilities here
if the will were there.
Patients that we're seeing
with nausea, vomiting, diarrhoea
symptoms easily cured.
We're trying to do as much as we
can to save as many as we can.
Some were literally
on death's door.
Without treatment, left alone,
those people would die.
But what hospitals
can't do alone is stop the
spread of disease, not without
addressing the root causes.
How clean is this water?
Very clean, we can
drink it ourselves.
Nahlah: At the core
of their work
is providing access
to clean water.
An hour away, Global Medic
treats water in bulk.
Each litre of clean water
costs less than half a penny.
The stuff that they're drinking
now, no wonder we're getting
cholera and outbreaks
of watery diarrhoea, right.
This is the solution. These
systems deliver clean water.
This is the only thing that's
going to save this crisis.
Nahlah: The water is shipped
to the camps directly.
Once there,
it quickly draws a crowd.
"This is the first time
we've received clean water,"
he says.
There's more the world
and Canada can do
to prevent the spread
of disease, says Singh.
We don't understand
enough about Pakistan.
We don't interact with them.
We have to understand the people
that are affected here, they're
not the rich, they're not
anti-Western people.
They're the poorest of the poor.
They really, really need help.
Nahlah: They may not
know Canada, but they are
grateful all the same.
Nahlah Ayed, CBC News,
Shikarpur, Pakistan.
Michael: By late September
the flood waters finally
began to recede. But vast areas
remained submerged.
And with fields still flooded,
and homes, schools and hospitals
destroyed, millions of people
still have nowhere to go.
The floods are estimated to
have caused about $47 billion
in damage, a huge sum for
a country as poor as Pakistan.
And experts continue to warn
that unless more is done
to help, political instability
can only make things worse.
And that is News In Review.
Don't forget to check out
our website at...
I'm Michael Serapio.
Thanks for watching.